Look, let's be honest with each other.
Um, for years, the prevailing wisdom in
AI has been deceptively simple. Toddler
logic. More is better. More data, more
parameters, more compute power. We've
been told, "Shovel internet text into
the gaping m of a neural network and it
will emerge Athenaike, wise, and
helpful." But here in 2026, that
approach is a spectacular failure. It's
like trying to become a gourmet chef by
eating everything in a grocery store.
Cleaning supplies, checkout candy.
You'll be full. You still won't know how
to cook. And you might think bleach
tastes interesting. Chasing data volume
alone is a fool's errand down a
dangerous path. These massive,
indiscriminately trained models are
masters of confident nonsense. They can
sound plausible. They can sound
authoritative. And they can be utterly,
fundamentally wrong.
Experts call this hallucination, which
means the AI is making things up, like a
child explaining where the cookies went.
So, what is this empathy gap? It's the
chasm between what a model knows and
what a user actually needs. A large
language model can ingest the entirety
of Wikipedia. It can ingest thousands of
books. It can ingest the chaotic mess of
the public internet. It can tell you the
capital of Burkina Faso. It can tell you
the molecular weight of caffeine. But it
can't learn how to be patient with a
confused student. It can't learn how to
offer encouragement to a struggling
artist. It can't learn how to provide
clear, simple steps to someone who is
already overwhelmed. Raw data is devoid
of intent, tone, and context. It teaches
facts, but not how to care. A tool that
doesn't care about its users goals is
ultimately a bad tool. This gap births
the most frustrating problems. Ask for a
simple recipe and you get a culinary
dissertation. The model isn't malicious,
it's clueless. It learned patterns from
professional cooking websites, not a
tired parents reality. The data taught
complexity, not utility. The empathy gap
also drives bias. If your data comes
from a world full of systemic biases,
spoiler, it does. Your model will learn
and amplify them, and it will sound
perfectly objective doing it. It's an
engine that laers prejudice into the
appearance of fact. Empathy is the
bridge across this gap. It makes us ask,
who are we building this for? So, how do
you actually practice this empathy in a
concrete way? You can't just write
import empathy in your code. Stop
designing for a vague mythical user.
Start designing for specific people.
This is where user personas come in. A
persona is not just a demographic
profile. It's a short narrative sketch
of a target user complete with a name, a
job, a core goal, a primary frustration.
It's a simple act of fiction grounded in
reality. And it is a shockingly powerful
tool for focusing a development team.
You are no longer building a generic
chatbot. You are building a tool for
Maria. Maria, a high school biology
teacher who needs creative, safe lab
ideas she can explain to 15year-olds in
under 5 minutes. Let's make this real.
Imagine you're fine-tuning a coding
assistant. Instead of one generic model,
be guided by a few key personas. Maria
the teacher, David the student coder,
Priya the data scientist. David, a
19-year-old CS student new to Python. He
needs clear step-by-step explanations
with lots of comments. He's terrified of
looking dumb in front of his professor.
Priya, a senior data scientist with a
decade of experience. The traditional
approach to fine-tuning often resembles
a massive oneshot cannon. Teams spend
weeks preparing a gigantic data set,
load it up, press the go button on a
cluster of GPUs for days and then
anxiously wait to see what comes out the
other end. It's slow, it's expensive,
and if the result is bad, it's
incredibly demoralizing. The design
thinking approach, however, treats
fine-tuning less like a cannon and more
like sculpting. You don't try to get it
perfect on the first try. Instead, you
embrace the idea of a low-fidelity
prototype. You start small, you start
fast, you start messy. Your first
fine-tuning run shouldn't use your
entire painstakingly curated data set.
Instead, take a small but representative
sample, your golden examples, and run a
quick, cheap training cycle. The goal
here is not to create a finished
product. The goal is to learn. This
first prototype will almost certainly
have flaws. It will misunderstand
prompts. It will adopt the wrong tone.
It will hallucinate wildly. But here's
the key. You treat these failures not as
bugs in the code, but as flaws in the
design. You analyze the bad outputs and
ask design- ccentric questions. Why did
the model get this so wrong? Was the
instruction unclear? Is our example for
a polite tone actually coming across as
robotic? For far too long, the AI
community has been obsessed with the
wrong report card. We measure our models
with abstract standardized benchmarks
and watch loss curves creep downwards,
celebrating when our line is slightly
lower than someone else's. This is like
judging a chef's skill based only on the
final weight of the food they produce.
It's a metric, sure, but it tells you
absolutely nothing about whether the
food is delicious, nutritious, even
edible. These old metrics are not
useless. They can tell you if your model
is learning something, but they are
dangerously incomplete. They tell us
nothing about whether the model is
useful, trustworthy, pleasant to
interact with. To build models that
truly serve people, we need to invent
and adopt new human focused measures of
success. This starts with creating a
custom alignment score for your project.
This isn't a single number, but a
composite score derived from several
qualitative assessments. You get a panel
of human raiders, people who represent
your user personas, to evaluate the
model's output on real world tasks. They
don't just rate it as correct or
incorrect. They rate it on multiple
axes.
Did it successfully complete the task?
Was the tone appropriate for the
situation? Was the information presented
clearly? Did it build trust or create
confusion? This provides a rich
multi-dimensional view of performance
that a simple accuracy score could never
capture. So here is the bottom line and
I need every engineer, every product
manager and every team lead to hear
this. Stop chasing raw data. Just stop.
That habit, the reflexive instinct to
solve a problem by finding a bigger data
set is holding us back. It is the single
greatest obstacle to building AI that is
genuinely helpful, reliable, and aligned
with human values. We have to change
this core behavior. We must treat the
large language model not as a passive
database to be filled, but as a product
to be designed, a partner to be trained.
The work is not done when the training
run starts. That is when the real work
of refinement and guidance begins. Here
is how you can start this shift today
with five clear actionable steps. First,
before you write a single line of tuning
code, create two or three simple user
personas. Give them names and problems.
Second, forget bulk data. Instead,
gather or write a small set of 50 to 100
golden examples that perfectly
demonstrate the desired behavior for
those personas. Third, run a fast,
low-fidelity fine-tune using only those
examples.