Let's talk about int
los
source intelligence intelligence
intelligence.
I'm going to try to find his
Snapchat account.  On her Snapchat account, well,
I'll find a pseudonym.  How am
I going to be able to pivot to this
pseudonym?
How to get started in INT and go from a
beginner to a true investigator?
Where to begin?  What are the
best resources?  Which tools
are truly useful?  These are
questions that many people ask themselves,
yet most take the
wrong direction from the start.  You
may think that it's enough to
learn tools, but that's
not what makes progress.  In this
video, I'm going to show you how to
really get started with Ozint and,
most importantly, how to avoid the mistakes that
block 90% of beginners.  But first, do
you really know what
osint is?  OINT stands for open
source intelligence, or in French, roso
for intelligence from an
open source.  In concrete terms, it is the ability
to collect, analyze and exploit
information that is publicly available
on the internet, in the media,
social networks, websites or even
official documents.  In this
video, I won't go into
detail about how to retrieve this
information, but if you're interested,
I've already done quite a bit of content on the
subject.  Today, Laint is used
in many fields and professions
almost everywhere information has
value.  To give you a few
examples, in journalism,
investigators use it to verify
facts, gather sources, and
uncover information that is
not immediately visible.
Similarly, analysts who follow
geopolitical conflicts use these
same techniques to observe
troop movements, understand
crisis dynamics and changes in
location over time from
public sources such as satellite images and
social media posts.  Companies also use it
extensively, particularly for
competitive intelligence, monitoring
market trends and anticipating the
movements of their competitors, which is
called
economic intelligence, or in recruitment
to better understand profiles and
verify the credibility of candidates.
One important point also needs to be clarified
.  Many people make
the mistake of confusing cybersecurity and cybersecurity.
In reality, it's clearly not the
same thing.  These disciplines can
intersect, for example to identify
threats or understand the context of an
attack.  But Laint remains above all a
skill that applies well beyond
cybersecurity in many
different professions.  If you want to
learn how to do Losint, it is
also important to know the
intelligence cycle because many
beginners jump straight into
information gathering without knowing what to
look for, how to sort the data, or
how to analyze it.  Its goal is
to enable you to transform
raw data into useful information and then
into actionable intelligence.  For
example, imagine that you follow the
Twitter account of a company or a
public figure.  Tweets,
likes, photos or shared links
are raw data.  By
analyzing them, you can spot
trends, projects or
partnerships in preparation, which
becomes useful information.  If you
correlate this information with other
public sources, you obtain
actionable intelligence, for example
to anticipate a launch or a
strategic decision.  Before you even
start our inint, it is very
important to master the legal framework.
Many people believe that because
information is public, it
can be used freely.  In France,
for example, simply
downloading data from a
data breach containing, for example,
usernames, passwords or
banking information is illegal and the
penalties are quite severe, up to 5
years in prison and a €375,000 fine.
Certain practices are also
obviously prohibited, such as
publishing personal information
about someone, which is called
doxing, and is also punishable by 3 years
imprisonment and a fine of €45,000.
To delve deeper into these topics, I
recommend the series of blogs written by
Marc-Antoine Ledieux, which explains
its legal limits very well and illustrates
everything with very well-
made images.  To begin your research, you absolutely must
not rush in headlong
without thinking about protecting your traces.
For this, what is called obsec for
Operational Security is essential.  And
the idea is simple.  Before collecting
information, you need to know
who you are protecting yourself against and how to avoid
leaving
sensitive information about yourself lying around.  In practice, this
involves several methods such as
using a secure browser
like Brave Thor and extensions to
limit tracking.  Use
encrypted messaging services like
session.Oio or signal.  Create fake
identities or sock puppets.  To
interact online without revealing your
real identity.  Use
virtual machines for each investigation to
isolate your activities.  Testing a
secure operating system like
Tails that leaves virtually no
trace on your computer, having a
disposable phone number for
registering on different sites, and
there are many other
techniques.  If this topic interests you,
I highly recommend
Michael Buzzel's book called Extreme Privacy and
watching my dedicated video on this subject
to delve deeper into it.  And one of the
first things I do to
protect myself is to use a VPN.  And the one I'm
using here is Proton
VPN.  Proton is a Swiss company
created in 2014 with one
main objective: your privacy.
Today they have over 100
million users and unlike
many other services, their
model is not based on
data collection.  In practice, when I activate
Proton VPN before launching this kind of
test, all my traffic goes through an
end-to-end encrypted tunnel.  This
means that neither my internet provider, nor
the websites I visit, nor the
shady stuff I download can
see my real IP address.  And in a
video like this, it's
essential.  What is
also interesting is that Proton, being based in
Europe, operates outside the
oversight of large
Texas-based companies.  This means that Proton
VPN keeps no logs of your activity
and all of this has been verified by
independent audits, which their competitors
cannot really guarantee.  Their
code is entirely open source, so
anyone can verify what they are
actually doing.  And since they are based
in Switzerland, your data is protected
by some of the strictest laws in the
world.  They also have one of the
strongest networks with over 18,000 servers
in more than 120 countries.  So you can
connect from almost anywhere
with very fast speeds.  And
of course it's available on all
devices and it's super easy to
install.  In short, if you pay even a little
attention to what you do
online, having a layer of protection
like that makes all the difference.  If you want to
try Proton VPN, you can get
up to 70% off with my link
in the description.  Now that you have
the basics, you need to understand that there are
many subdomains of HalloSint,
each with its own techniques and
concrete use cases.  To begin with,
there is, for example, Sockmint for
Social Media Intelligence.  Here, we
work on social media.
In practical terms, it can be used, for
example, to find all accounts
linked to a person from a
phone number or email address, or to
analyze interactions, subscribers,
and likes to rebuild a network
and understand the behavior of a
target.  Then there is goint and
limint which consist of analyzing
images.  A very concrete example is
trying to find the
exact location of a photo.  For example, by
analyzing a building's shadow on a
sign or even vegetation.  Then,
by using Google Maps Street View or
other services, it is sometimes possible
to find precisely where an image or
even a video was taken.  You
also have website recognition or
recon.  The goal here is to collect as much
information as possible about a site.
The technologies used, the
subdomains are historical, and the
IP addresses are used to understand its
structure.  It is widely used in
cybersecurity, particularly in the
reconnaissance phase.  Another
important area is Finint, which stands for
financial intelligence.  Here, for example, we will
analyze a company from
public records, see who its
managers are, analyze documents,
links between companies or detect
suspicious financial arrangements.  And finally,
you have the signint for
intelligence obtained from the interception of
electronic signals.  Even if
part of it falls outside the scope of LosINT, it
may involve analyzing
public communication frequencies or analyzing
radio data accessible in
certain contexts.  In reality, there are
many other
areas.  And if all this vocabulary
interests you, I recommend you go
to the Intopia website which brings together these
terms with definitions and
concrete examples.  Now we're going to
talk about a skill that
literally changes the way you
use the internet: the Google Dark King.
Most people, and maybe even
you, use their search engine
in a very basic way.  You type in a
few keywords, click on the
first results and that's it.
But if you want to find
really interesting information,
you need to learn to speak
Google's language using search operators
to precisely target
results.  For example, you can
use operators like site to
target a specific site, file type to
search for specific formats like
PDF, Excel or Word.  Use `Intitle`
to search for words in
a page title.  In URL to filter
specific URLs.  And the quotation marks are to
ask the search engine to
find exactly that sequence of words
in the same order.  Specifically, a
search like site.tesla.com
fileype PDF in quotes car will
allow you to find only
PDF documents containing the word car
on the Tesla website.  To go
further, you have resources that
exist such as the Google Hacking
database which brings together thousands of
queries already prepared to find
specific information.  There are even
sites like DOC GPT to
automatically generate queries based on
your prompt.  Moreover, if you
want to go much further on the
subject, I have already made a complete video
dedicated to Google Ding where I detail
many concrete examples and
use cases that you can
easily reproduce.  But even if you master
all of that perfectly, there is one reality
you will surely encounter.
Some information disappears.  A
website that changes, a page deleted, a
tweet erased, an account that no
longer exists.  And if you arrive too late, you
get the impression that the information is
lost.  In reality, nothing ever
truly disappears from the internet.  Tools like WB
Machine or archive.ph PH allow you to
view older versions of
web pages, sometimes dating back several
years.  In practical terms, this allows you to
see what a site looked like at a given
moment, to see its old
deleted versions and analyze its
evolution over time, even if
today the content has been modified or
deleted.  And that's precisely why
capture and preservation are
fundamental.  A good habit to adopt is
to archive all the
important information you come across.
However, be careful because it is
possible that the page you have just
archived may be accessible and visible
to other people as well.  To
effectively preserve information,
several complementary techniques exist
.  The first is
screenshots.  To do this, there
are tools, including
extensions capable of
capturing and recording complete web pages
and creating folders with
all the information visible at a
specific moment.  Then there is
note-taking.  A tool like Obsidian is
extremely powerful for this, to create
a structured knowledge base with
links between your notes, folders
and even templates that we follow specifically
for the purpose.  But there is an even higher level than
visualization.  This is where
tools like Osin Tracker come in
. They allow you to create graphs
where you can link entities together –
people, websites,
companies, accounts, email addresses – and
suddenly you see
connections that you might never have
noticed otherwise.  At this stage,
it is essential to understand one
fundamental thing.  Methodology is
far more important than tools.
Tools, even the most efficient ones, are
constantly changing, becoming
obsolete or losing their effectiveness.  In
Noint, this methodology is based on
several pillars.  critical analysis skills
, curiosity, and rigor.
You must be able to structure
your research, take a step back from
what you find, and not be
trapped by
hasty conclusions.  And above all, you need to be
aware of the cognitive biases that
can distort your perception of
reality or lead you to make
irrational decisions.  For
example, there is confirmation bias, in which
you only look for
information that confirms what you
already believe and ignore the rest.  There
are many other biases.  And if
this topic interests you, I
highly recommend this resource which
explains how our brain can
deceive us and how to remain critical.
Once you have managed to obtain
several pieces of information, you also need to
learn to pivot, that is, to move
from one clue to another.  For example, an
email can lead you to a profile, then
to a website, then to a company, and so
on.  But be careful,
not all information is equal.
Never rely on a single source to
validate information.  The more
independent sources you have confirming
a fact, the more you can
trust it, especially by giving preference to
official sources.  As you have
understood, there are tons of tools
for making osint and not all of them have
the same use depending on what you are
trying to do.  I'm not going to go into
detail about all the
existing tools, but I'll give you a
short list of all the ones I find
really interesting and practical.
First, to in Industries and Epios to
analyze email addresses,
phone numbers and pseudonyms to see the
associated accounts.  What's my name?  A
really cool tool for finding
accounts linked to a username on different
websites, forums, etc.  Overpass
Turbo to leverage Open
Street Map data.  Ideal for
precise geographic searches, Search by Image.
A very cool extension for doing
reverse image searches and
finding the origin of a photo,
identifying similar images or
finding a location.  Gimple to
analyze the exive metadata of an
image.  Google Earth Pro to analyze
satellite images and visualize
geographical areas in detail with a
history to go back in time.
Wi to retrieve information about
domains and
website owners.  Blockchain Explorer.  If you
want to track transactions on the
blockchain and if you want to go
even further, I advise you to
take a look at the toolbox of
Belling Cat and Ozint FR which includes
hundreds of Oosint tools classified
by category.  Learning Zint
is like cybersecurity; it's
not enough to just read or watch
tutorials, you also have to practice.
And one of the best ways is to
start with yourself by trying to
discover your own publicly available traces
.  At the same time, take this opportunity
to remove anything that can
enhance your anonymity.  To go
further, there are also small
challenges and training platforms
in French, also called CTFs.  I
particularly recommend sitesia,
for fun, Isfred, which offer
very cool challenges of different
types.  Each one has its own
perfect scenarios for starting to
practice.  There is also the
Sopia Santos website and videos in English with
very educational challenges for
beginners.  And for those who
really want to immerse themselves in it, there are
also more official CFUIN events open to
everyone, taking place over
several days in teams with
very interesting scenarios.
Personally, I do it very often
and it's great for making
rapid progress.  Coming soon, for
example, there is the CTF Bleuet de France organised
by the Ozint éveille club of the AEGE, the
Milague 3 organised by Oscar Zuluou and
the CTF of the 20 years of the European school
of economic intelligence.  Along the same
lines, I recommend this book by
Michael Bazel, which is a bit like an
ultra-comprehensive bible for learning
lots of things to conduct investigations
effectively.  Once you
start practicing, you need to understand
something fundamental.  It's a
field that's evolving very quickly.  Every
day, new tools, techniques and
methods appear.  That's why
monitoring and following current events
is absolutely essential.  To
stay up to date, I advise you to
follow active accounts on
social media, for example Project
Fox, Blinkat or Benjamin Strick who
regularly publish on real cases,
tutorials, tools and
discussions that will allow you to
stay informed on these subjects.  In
addition, subscribe to
newsletters that summarize news,
tools, new publications
and the latest tips from the
community.  Among the most useful ones
you have are The OIN Newsletter, Field
Notes and OIN Ambition.  In addition,
I also advise you to follow
pages and organizations that
regularly publish very
interesting articles.  For example, the
Bellingat group, which I've already mentioned,
publishes analyses that I love on
very detailed concrete cases, particularly on
conflicts, investigations or
information verification,
explaining their method precisely.  And on the
French-speaking side, you also have
Project Fox which offers very
interesting content, whether it be articles or
analyses, and above all, don't stay
alone.  Joining active communities
is a great way to learn
faster, find people to
progress with, and stay motivated.  Once again
, we find
Oscar Zou, Project Fox, Blinkat and my
Discord server which also contains a
section dedicated to Losint.  Finally, there
are specialized training courses and programs
that will allow you to
structure your learning,
including classic programs in
economic intelligence such as those offered
by GE and EIE.  Recently, there are
also 100% online courses like the one at
A3 University.  And in
some cybersecurity training courses,
there are also sometimes modules
dedicated to LosINT.  For a first
concrete contact with the field, the little MINTIN
FR is ideal to give you some
nice basics.  If you enjoyed this video,
please like, share and
subscribe to support me and not
miss future videos.
THANKS.  Mr.