Why is branding perceived as
a money pit?  My name is Théo,
I am the founder of Kouudac, your
favorite ads agency.  So, it's one of my
fiancées who is rational.  When
managing an advertising budget with
weekly objectives, the idea of
putting budget on branding
seems like an abstraction because
campaigns must be justified with a
ROS, an acquisition cost, a
conversion volume, therefore content that
builds an image in quotation marks
without direct attribution or line in
the dashboard.  It's difficult to
defend in this context.  The resistance
is therefore normal.  It comes from a
context where every euro must be
justified quickly.  And where
analytical tools have accustomed everyone
to an almost
surgical level of granularity, we know that each
campaign reported the day before.  So
when something escapes this
logic, the reflex is to be wary of it.
This reflex is not
irrational, moreover.  It reflects a real
constraint.  So what does
branding actually change?  Let's
take a real-life example.  Tête blonde is a
brand of handcrafted jewelry that we
support.  We started with
classic work involving
campaign structuring,
optimization, cleaning, and so on.
Everything you do when you take over an
account.  At a certain point, everything had been done
well, but it was no longer enough.
All the obvious levers had been
exhausted, and that's when we made a
change in nature.  We started to
broadcast content focused on the
founder, her creative process,
handmade items, the making of the pieces,
and so on.  This is where the brand
began to establish its
own identity, a uniqueness that made it
recognizable and, above all, desirable.  And
the results have
improved significantly compared to the
previous year, without any transformation of the
product or the offer.  In fact, the
lever we used here was
perception.  And perception acts on
something very concrete.  This is the
economic value of a buyer over
time.  An advertiser who creates
brand loyalty sees their
customers return, repurchase, and
recommend.  Over a 6-month period,
the difference between a loyal customer and
a customer who disappears is considerable
in terms of the overall profitability of
acquisition campaigns.  On this subject, the measure
exists but it requires a different
reference point.  Attributing a
sale directly to a branding campaign is
structurally impossible.  No
tracking tool, however sophisticated,
can change that.  Branding
influences a perception that is built up
over several weeks and sometimes even
several months.  But several signals
allow us to read its effects.  The
progress of searches for the
brand name in Google Search Console is
increasing.  There is also the evolution of the
repurchase rate.  Obviously, these are
trends, not immediate proof, and that's how they
should be treated as
indicators of direction.  We can
also objectively assess the strength of a
brand with a fairly revealing test.  We
take any text from the brand,
remove the logo and check if we
can identify it by reading it alone.  If
the message is interchangeable with
that of any competitor, the
brand does not really have its
own existence.  You can imagine
how delicate it is for an
agency to point this out to one of its
clients without offending them.  And we can even
take the exercise further by
comparing the brand's vocabulary and
arguments to those of the market.  When we
come across a high similarity rate,
it is a factual piece of data.  It allows us to
move beyond aesthetic judgment.  The brand
speaks like everyone else, and its
potential buyers perceive it even
without being able to name it.  So
now, why do some people get through it while
others remain stuck?
E-commerce brands that exceed the
threshold of around 1 to 2 million euros
in revenue share a
common characteristic.  They all agreed at some
point not to measure an
immediate return on part of their
advertising investment.  They
made the bet of installing something
for the long term, and this choice does not imply
massive budgets.  You can start
building your brand with
reasonable means and without excessive risk.  What is
changing, and this is precisely where
it gets stuck for many advertisers,
is the time horizon that we accept.
Major brands invest in
their image because they know that it is what
determines their
performance in the medium and long term.  To
achieve this, we must start by
reasoning like her, with the same
patience regarding the results.  This level of
maturity goes far beyond the
weekly management of budgets.  It
rarely develops on its own.  This is often where
the role of a marketing director
becomes truly meaningful.  All brands
that have passed this milestone made the same
choice at some point: to accept
not measuring everything immediately.  It is
therefore a management decision taken with
a longer horizon because unfortunately
brands that continue to optimize
their campaign on a weekly basis
often remain where they are.  So here's a quick
summary of this video in case you didn't
quite follow along.  Branding is
often dismissed on the grounds that it is
impossible to measure and offers no
guaranteed return.  This mistrust is totally
understandable, but it is based on a
confusion of frameworks.  Almost all
e-commerce brands that have reached a
significant growth stage have
integrated a branding dimension
into their advertising strategy.  What ultimately
divides advertisers on this subject
is less a question of heroism
than a question of horizon.  That was
for Kouudac, your favorite news agency.
If you would like to have
your acquisition strategy reviewed by a
specialist, you can book a
discovery call using the link in the
description of this video.  I'll see you next time
.