You play a game every day and the
worst part is you don't even know
you're playing.
You wake up, you get ready and you
go to work.
You're trading your time for
money.  You collect your winnings and move forward
like millions of other
players.  You make progress to pay your
rent, fill your fridge, then go on
vacation and start all over again.
Then, over time, it starts to seem
normal, as if the game had always been meant to
work that way.
But let's look at the highest point.  It's
not just life, it's a
game board with its squares, its cards and
above all its own rules.  And
recently, a fundamental rule
of the game has begun to change.   Will
artificial intelligence
put us all out of work?
Microsoft has announced the layoff of
nearly 4% of its workforce in order to
refocus more on AI.
Job apocalypse.
Among those who work with their
ideas, among those who work with
their bodies, something begins to
move.  But before understanding what
is changing, we must first
understand what game we have been playing from the
beginning.
Like any type of game, it starts with
a tutorial.  And in this one, the
tutorial has a name: the school.
Officially, it's the place where you
learn to read,
to count,
to understand the world,
to encounter your first
injustices.
But unofficially, it's also
the place where you learn to become
compatible with the set.  From a very young age,
the first rules of the game are taught:
to respect fixed schedules, to sit for
long periods, to
respect authority,
to be evaluated by your superior,
and to memorize rather than understand.
And most importantly, the tutorial teaches you a
central promise.  If you play well, you'll
get a place.  If you work hard, if you
do what is expected, if you get the
right results, then the platform will help you
move forward.
But
this tutorial does something even
more important.
He deals the first cards of the
game.
So, let's draw the first card.
Interesting.  The postal code.  Growing up
in a place where schools are more
stable, better supported, better funded
with more information, more
confidence, more opportunities.  Others say
no, and without even mentioning talent, the
game doesn't quite start
on the same playing field.
OK.  The second is networking: a contact,
a close friend, a relative who knows the
rules, someone who can
recommend you, open a door for you.  Because
very often, the first
opportunities don't just come to the
best players, they also come
to those who already know which door to
knock on.
The third is
orientation.
At that age, many players do
not choose a voice.  They
simply follow the one that the plateau makes
most accessible.
And the last and most powerful card,
the cultural capital of your family, the
words we hear at home, the way
we talk about work, money,
studies, risk, what is
possible for us and what is
not.  And even though the game can
always change, the starting hand
often influences the first few turns
. Because at this stage, you're
not yet questioning the game.  What you
really want is to get in, find your place,
be validated, become useful.
The cards are dealt, the tutorial
ends, and for most
players, the first big space that
comes next is almost always the
same: the employee board.
Before returning to this set, I
forgot one last card, the partner
of this video.  If you start a business and
want to leave the salaried position,
you need an official address.  And that's
precisely what this registered
office provider does.  You can register your
business online, choose from over
50 prestigious addresses and
view your mail which has been
carefully digitized.  So if you're
starting your business and want a
simple solution to set up your registered office
properly, you can check out this business
address provider.  Thank you to them for sponsoring
this video.  Alright, let's start playing.
Rule number 1, time.
In this game, the mechanics are quite
simple.  You exchange your time cards and
skill cards for
money.
More specifically, you sell your time to
an organization and in exchange, they
pay you a regular salary.
Each day, you simply receive a
new hand, 24 one-hour cards on
paper.  It seems like a lot, but as soon as
you put them on the table, the
mechanics become much more brutal.
H cards go to sleep,
16 remain. H cards go to work, H
remain. Then come the
invisible squares.
And suddenly, your day is no longer a
large empty space.  It's a remnant,
a few scattered cards on which you
have to fit your social life, your
family, your health, your rest and sometimes
your personal ambitions.  Some people
are trying to cheat the rules.
It draws on sleep, but this is
not a sustainable strategy; it is a
loan taken out on the body, and the body
always ends up demanding its debt.
In short, if all your cards go to
work, your game is paused and you
have to wait until the next day to
get a new deck.  This is the first
mechanic of the game: time versus
money.  This system has a
huge advantage.  It is stable and the
reward comes every month.  But that time for him is not
enough.
Rule number 2, the skills cards.
Two people can work 8 hours
without creating the same value.  For what ?
Because in this game, not all cards are created equal
.  Some are
common, others are rare, some
are easy to replace,
others much less so.
If what you know how to do can be
found everywhere, then what you
bring to the table is cheaper.  But if what
you know how to do is rare, useful, and
difficult to reproduce, then its value
increases.  Because in this system, you're
not paid simply for being there.  You are
paid because your presence
generates more value than it
costs.  Otherwise, there's no reason
to keep you in the game.  And over
time, some players develop
their cards.  They are improving.
Rule number 3, the logic of the board.
At first, you apply, you execute, you
learn the rules of the board.  Your
value still largely depends on your
presence.
Level 2.
Then over time, you gain in
speed, reliability, autonomy, and
understanding.  You do it better, faster,
with fewer mistakes.  So, you
bring in more money.  Level 3.
Sometimes the game changes.  You're no longer just playing
your own cards.  You
also help others to play theirs better
.  You coordinate, you streamline, you
transmit, you arbitrate, you make the
system more efficient around you.  And
this role is worth more because it no
longer relies solely on execution,
but on the ability to advance
several pieces at the same time.
Level 4.
For a minority of players, after
many years, the game changes
level again.  He no longer
just executes, he no longer just coordinates
.  It begins to influence the very way
the set functions.
Now you no longer see a simple
game, you see a machine.  On this
platform, some directly produce
value.   They are the ones
who transform efforts
into something real.  Without them, there is
nothing to exchange.
Nothing to sell, nothing to trade,
but producing is not enough.
Because a sum of isolated actions does
not yet create a system.
Then others organize,
distribute the roles, and
coordinate the teams.
They take scattered efforts and
transform them into a
coherent machine.
And then there's what actually drives
the game.
Who sets the priorities,
who decides where to put the energy,
which projects deserve time, which
positions should be eliminated, which risks are
worth taking?  And finally, there are those
who finance, those who own, who
inject the funds, those who can
accelerate a plateau or let it
die.  Up to this point, the logic of the board
remained clear.  You started at the bottom, you leveled up
, gaining value with
time, experience, and mastery.
In other words, progress in this part
requires one simple thing:
time.  Real, years, time
to learn, time to make mistakes.  And that's
precisely where something
started to go wrong because a new
player entered the game and he doesn't
play with the same limits as
you.
A new player has been detected.
Rule of broken time.
This new player has no
ceiling.  He doesn't sleep, he doesn't get
tired, he doesn't take breaks,
he doesn't get sick, he doesn't stop
at 6 p.m.
And suddenly, the first major rule
of the board begins to crack.  An
increasing part of the production can
be delegated to a player who has no
biological constraints.
Rules of competence.
This new player doesn't develop his
skills like we do.  He doesn't
learn them.  He does not embody them.  He doesn't
always understand them the way a
human understands them.  Instead, it
absorbs thousands of
skill cards created by humans.  He is
reproducing tasks faster and faster
that yesterday required years
of experience to be executed
correctly.  And this is where the game
becomes unsettling because, for the
first time, skills that
seemed protected begin to lose
some of their rarity.  The logic of the game
board is destroyed.
For a very long time, the
economic logic of the plateau was simple.  To
produce more, a company needed to
recruit more people.  More customers, more
employees, more operations, more
teams, more complexity, more
human players.   That's how
organizations
grew by adding
human hands.  For the first time, a
company can seek to grow without
proportionally increasing the number
of human players on the board.
Replacement in progress.   That's
the real turning point.
Not
exactly very reassuring, is it?
He says that the impact of the [unclear] on the
world prevents him from sleeping at night.  One
can cite Dario Amodi, the head
of Enthropique, who estimates that
50% of white-collar jobs will
disappear in the next 5 years.
Quite radical.  And Musk also says that
we
humans will have to rethink the meaning of our lives in a
world where AI will be able to do everything for
us within a few years.
And perhaps that's what awaits us
with this tornado of
artificial intelligence.  It's starting to get scary.
Some see this tornado arriving
by 2028.
So, let's imagine a board where this player
continues to progress,
where he takes up more and more space,
more and more tasks, more and more
decisions.  A game board where,
gradually, certain spaces no
longer need to be occupied by
human players to continue
functioning.
So, what's going on?
What happens is that some
squares start to empty without the
game stopping.  The results are still coming in
, companies are
still producing, but the human element is
starting to become less obvious.
And that's where the vertigo begins.
For a long time, work was never
solely about earning money.  It
served another purpose, to give a role,
a rhythm, a legible place on the
stage.  He said, "This is what you're good for
. This is where you go in the morning. This is
why you're here."  That's why the
question is so frightening because when
someone asks "Is Lia going to
replace my job?"  What he's
often really asking is, "Will there
still be a clear place for me
in this world? What if certain
roles become blurred? What if
certain skills cease to be a
safeguard? Then it's not just
an economic shock, it's an
identity shock. And that shouldn't be
underestimated. There will be destruction.
Entire professions will be redefined.
Tasks will disappear. Roles
will be emptied, people will find themselves caught
between two versions of the world,
and in all major transitions,
there will always be a brutal zone, the one
where the old system dies before
the new one is even legible.
But perhaps that's the easiest mistake
to make: seeing this new player
as a pure enemy, as if history
were going to boil down to a duel between
humans and machines. That's
probably not what's
happening because this player isn't
just replacing the old; it's also
amplifying and accelerating the existing order.
And since the dawn of time, this is
n't the first time."  that humanity sees
its rules changing.
Each time, certain positions have
disappeared, but each time
new cards have appeared,
new ways of creating,
new rarities,
new forms of value. The printing press,
industry, the internet haven't only
destroyed. Perhaps the real
change isn't man versus
machine. Perhaps the real
change is man with a
new teammate in a game whose
rules have just been rewritten. If
producing faster becomes commonplace, then
what regains value is perhaps something else
. The ability to
connect ideas, to understand
humans, their emotions, to build
trust, to give direction, to
sense what deserves to exist in a
world where almost everything can be
generated. Because ultimately, if these tools
give us more power, then perhaps the
real question is no longer
how to produce more. The real question
becomes what do we choose to do
with this power? Do we
use it to accelerate the process even further?  Noise?
More fatigue? More
overproduction?
Where do we use it to free up
time? To better care for others, to
learn better, to understand better, to better
protect what until now was too
slow, too fragile, or not profitable enough
to be truly noticed? And
suddenly the game changes because if
almost everything becomes feasible, then what
really matters is no longer
just what we can do, but what we
decide to make more humane.
Perhaps, deep down, that's the
feeling of our time: opening our
eyes and feeling this fear that something
is shifting, that it's already too
late to return to the
world as it was. Understanding that the ground we
thought was stable wasn't so stable after all
.
Feeling almost instantly that our reference points and
certainties are
beginning to crumble.
Falling with the impression that the rules
are changing before we even understand them,
and discovering in the midst of this fall
that we may not just be
losing an old world,
we may be...  Already entering
a new game. And the real
question now isn't just
whether we'll fall? The real
question is, once in the new
game, how do we decide to play?