2015 Staton Island, United States.
It is late at night when a man
named Anthony Coronati picks up a package
of illegal drugs he bought on
a bodybuilding forum.
Upon arriving at the delivery address, he
notices that the package is much
larger than usual
and when he lifts it, he hears a much
louder clicking sound than expected.
The situation seems suspicious to him and
instead of following his usual route,
he decides to take the safest way home
.  Coronati puts
the package in his backpack and walks a
few blocks until he
finds a taxi.
He then leads him to a
deserted street a few kilometers away.
From there, he slips into a blind corner
of a narrow alley and enters an
old building.
Inside, he quickly changes his
clothes, stuffs his backpack into a
garbage bag and leaves through another exit.
Finally, he simply walks down the street
until he reaches his apartment.
Once home, he puts the box on his
bed, grabs his card and opens it.
But for some unknown reason, it is
not filled with osteoids.
Instead, it contains dozens of
bottles of dietary supplements.  He
takes one, opens it and takes out a
tablet.  It is coloured and has an
engraving on it.  That's when he realizes
that instead of receiving
steroids, he was sent a few
kilos of what looks like
MDMA pills.  Coronati is completely
disoriented and decides to contact Liston
is here, his online retailer, to
ask for news about the package.
A few minutes later, he receives
a reply.  Liston is here explains to him
that he accidentally sent the
wrong package and that if Coronati
resends it to a certain address, he will
pay him $1400 in
compensation.  Coronati, thinking it
was an accident, agrees to
resend the package to what he believes to
be a simple customer.  However, what he doesn't know is that
this will not be
an isolated case and that he has just been
recruited into an
international drug cartel on the Dark Web.
An organization that ships tons
of drugs around the world, earns
tens of millions of dollars, and has
created a near-perfect online cartel.
Before we continue, I'd like to
talk to you about Leo.
His usernames and passwords have just been
compromised and at this
precise moment, he no longer really has
control.  However, he could have seen it
coming with Nord VPN's dark web monitoring
.  He could have been alerted as soon as
his personal information
started circulating.  I myself recently
discovered that one of
my passwords had been leaked and without this
tool, I probably would never have
known.  And if you think it only
happens to other people, ask yourself this
question.  How many passwords will be
leaked in 2025?  500 million, 5
billion or 16 billion?  The reality
is the third answer, the
biggest data leak ever
recorded, and this is probably just the
beginning.  But Nord VPN is also, as
its name suggests, a VPN that
allows you to secure your connection and
browse much more
privately.  Your IP address is masked,
your data is encrypted, and you are
protected against malicious websites and
intrusive advertisements.  And there are
also much simpler uses,
such as accessing content that is
unavailable in your country.  For
example, I really want to rewatch
No Country for Old Man, but
unfortunately, it's not available in France.
But thanks to this site, I see that it is
only available in Canada.  So I changed
my location there and miraculously,
my movie was available again.  So, if
you want to try it, now is the time
because right now you get 4 months
free on 2-year subscriptions,
which works out to just under €3 per
month.  You have 30 days to try it,
satisfaction guaranteed or your money back.  So
basically, you can use it,
form your own opinion and
then decide.  Everything is in the
description.  Thank you NordVPN.
January 2017, North Carolina, United States
.
It is late at night and several
DEA agents are
currently monitoring a woman they suspect
of being a Dark Web drug trafficking legend
known as
Liston is here.  At that time, Liston
isir was a well-known figure in the
dark web.  It has been active since at
least 2012 and sells products via Silk
One, Silk Two, Alphabet and a whole
host of other dark web marketplaces.  She
specializes in pills,
particularly MDMA and
bansodiapesin, but also sometimes sells
other substances such as
steroids.  But let's get back to the
monitoring team.  She has been watching the suspect
for days, hoping she will
make a mistake.  But the woman
seems to know what she's doing.  She is keeping a
low profile and apart from the packages that
appear to have come from her, the authorities
have no evidence to arrest her or
search her home.
But that night, something was
different.
One
of the officers sees her getting rid of a
suspiciously large garbage bag.  This
arouses his curiosity and he decides to
get his hands on her bags.  But
when he looks at the time, he realizes
that the woman has carefully
calculated her cost because the garbage truck is now only a
few meters from their
street.  And if he doesn't act immediately,
any potential evidence will disappear forever
.
It is the middle of the night and
while his suspect sleeps, the officer
begins to search her garbage.  It
seems like a total waste of time at
first, but when he gets to the second
bag, he finds a shimmering yellow substance
and there is a lot of it, more
precisely more than a kilo of MDMA powder
and that changes everything.
January 18, 2017, Buncombe County,
North Carolina.
This is Amanda Troll, a 31-year-old woman from
North Carolina.  She is
currently speaking with an
employee at the Buncam County
Steak House restaurant and is asking him to
reserve a table for her for the next day.
It's for his mother's 67th birthday
and Troll, who hasn't seen her for
some time, wants to make
this an unforgettable moment.
Troll's father has been absent from her life
since she was 5 years old.  And even though it wasn't
easy, her brother and mother were
always there for her,
supporting her through her many
difficulties and helping her when she
needed it most.
The next day, Troll starts his day
in a good mood, happy to see his
mother again.
But around 4 p.m., as she was putting on her
shoes to leave, she heard a
commotion in her building.
Suddenly, the door bursts open and
a team of police officers bursts in
to arrest him.  Meanwhile, it's
almost 7pm and Troll's mother is
still sitting in the restaurant,
completely alone.  She has been waiting for
almost two hours and has called her daughter
several times without response.  She
thinks Amanda has forgotten her
birthday dinner when in reality
she is being questioned
at the police station.  Even worse, in
his apartment, officers found
more than 59 kg of MDMA, 14 kg of ketamine
and a whole host of other
illegal substances.  However, during
the interrogation, Troll reveals something
unexpected.  According to her, she is
not the person behind Liston is
here.  She is merely a pawn in a
larger operation, claiming that she is just one
of many resellers
working for Liston.
In reality, on many
Dark Web drug marketplaces,
sellers do not always ship the
products themselves to customers.  They
instead resort to various methods to
conceal the link between themselves and
the buyer.  One of them is to
use freight forwarders.  Freight
forwarders like Troll receive
shipments from the source or
another freight forwarder who then ask them
to repackage the parcel and
send it to a new address, either
that of the customer or that of another
freight forwarder.  In this way, the
authorities cannot trace the operation
directly back to its source,
allowing the mastermind behind it
to remain anonymous.  It would appear that
Troll experienced
financial difficulties a few years ago and
that a certain Benjamin Rotten introduced him to
the field of
expeditionary work.  Finally, Rotton
also put her in contact with the
alleged ringleader known only as
Liston is here.  Liston
explained to her that she could earn
between $800 and $1400 per shipment and
that he would send her four to seven packages per
month, each accompanied by
precise instructions on how to proceed.
However, the number of shipments
quickly increased
exponentially.  According to
Troll's sworn statement, she allegedly
sent over 4200 packages to addresses
all over the United States, Canada,
Jamaica, and even Ireland.  The fate of
Benjamin Rotten is unknown, but
Troll decided to cooperate with the
police and revealed that one address stood out
.
A house in Staten Island.
This address had both sent and
received dozens of packages from trolls,
suggesting that it is the
next mailing address in Liston's criminal network.
March 1, 2017, Staton Island.
It is early morning and
New York narcotics officers have 4.5
kg of MDMA tablets in their
car.  They go to an
abandoned house where they drop off the package and then
ask the
United States Postal Inspection Service to confirm the
deposit in their system.  Then they
wait for someone to come and collect
the package.
A few hours later, a man
arrives at the house.  As soon as he crosses
the gate, the team of plainclothes police officers
springs into action.
and stops him.
The man has been identified as
Anthony Coronati.  An
interesting fact is that a man is also associated with a
2014 fraud case in
which one Anthony Coronati,
also from Staton Island,
ran a hedge fund called B to
Task LLC.  But instead of investing
people's money, he
simply took it and used it for
his personal expenses such as
cosmetic surgery and trips to
the Caribbean.  In any case,
Coronati also claims to work
for a certain Liston, insisting
that his entry into the
reshipping business began with a
failed steroid purchase a few
years ago, followed by the
calculated manipulation of Istone and the promise
of easy money.  It is interesting to
note that he specifies that he bought
steroids on the regular web and that he
initially contacted Liston not via
encrypted messaging but through
a bodybuilding forum on which
Liston had indicated the email address
listonis here@gmail.com
as a means of contact.  Several
Liston profiles were found in
dark web marketplace databases
and on his Silcrot 2.0 profile he
indicates an onion email address.  This
shows that the Gmail address Coronati
provided to the authorities was created
by Liston before he even knew
how to properly conceal his
identity.  This means that thanks to
Coronat's email address, the police
now have a direct link to
the person hiding behind his
pseudonyms.  Better still, she
now has two compromised members of
the organization as well as a pile of
incoming packages that she can trace back to
their source.  And almost all of
Liston's parcels come from there.
from the same place.
October 2017, Coventry, United Kingdom.
It is around midnight when Bad
Mitzing, a 33-year-old Indian man, enters
one of the post offices in Coventry.
He has some packages to mail addressed to
an apartment in North Carolina,
USA.  The clerk
glances at the package and notes that the
sender's address appears to have been
entirely fabricated.  However, this doesn't
bother him and he
accepts.  The man pays for the package and leaves
.  But what he doesn't know is that across
the street, agents from the
British National Crime Agency, in
cooperation with agents from the
American DEA, are monitoring each of these
movements.  He believes he is the
mastermind behind the Liston organization.
It is very likely that a joint team of
British and American law enforcement officers will begin
monitoring several post offices in
Coventry.  This team then draws up
a list of people exhibiting
suspicious behavior such as sending
packages daily,
regularly changing post offices, and
especially sending packages without a
valid return address.  Finally, the police
registered Badmit Singeveillance
and when a package linked to him arrived at
the address of a compromised forwarder, law
enforcement was able to confirm
that Sing was indeed the person behind
the iston.  In any case, once
the authorities designate him as the
new prime suspect, she discovers a whole
series of inconsistencies in his
finances.  Indeed, he owns several
companies under the name Antilia, but none
of them generate profits, and
yet he somehow leads
a more than
comfortable lifestyle.  The task force in the
United Kingdom then quickly alerted the
American authorities and given
the amount of drugs and money that
passed through SI alias
Liston's organization, the American agencies decided
to take action.
April 26, 2019, Coventry, United Kingdom.
It is about 4 a.m. and two
cars with tinted windows are speeding
through the deserted streets of
Coventry.  Inside are
some members of the armed special forces
on their way to
Sing's home.  Everyone knows that the operation must take place
as quickly as possible.
Sing could erase the data from his
computers in seconds, and if
that happened, much of his
evidence could disappear forever.
When they arrive at their destination, the
doors suddenly open and they
immediately run towards the door and break
it down.  But before he realizes
what is happening, the first agent is
already in his room and Sin finds himself
facing the barrel of a rifle.  He was arrested
without resisting and thanks to the
officers' quick action, he was unable to
dispose of the evidence.  Inside
her home, law enforcement officers
found numerous pieces of evidence,
but most importantly, they discovered a
wallet containing 3838 Bitcoin on one
of her devices.  And after
analyzing the transaction history,
they established a link between
most of these bitcoins and
Liston's activities.  S is now on his way to
a British prison while the
United States begins its battle to
secure his extradition.  But for
more than 4 years, nothing happened and
after exhausting his appeal, he
was extradited to the oya in March 2023.
There, he spent another year
in prison until he
finally accepted a
plea agreement in 2024. And under the terms
of this agreement, he promised to surrender
all of his bitcoins, which were worth
more than $150 million
at that time.  But that's where
things get
interesting again.
Transaction records reveal that he received at
least 8000 bitcoins from
drug sales.  But Sin claims that he only has
access to 3838 of them which were
actually seized during the
2019 raid. However, according to
some allegations, he
transferred a large portion of this
money to the person behind
the Gmail account
akaa.parvinder@gmail.com.
It turns out that this address belongs
to Parinder Sin, Badmith's brother.  And
even though there is no proof, it is
extremely likely that some,
if not all, of the
remaining 4000 bitcoins was sent to
Parinder.  Either as a security measure,
or because Parvinder is actively
part of Liston's cartel.  At that
time, 4000 Bitcoins were worth
approximately $150 million.
April 25, 2024, somewhere in India,
after a series of flights and
car journeys, Ban Midin finally arrives at his
family's home.  There, he is welcomed by
his brother, Vinder, his father and
some other family members.
He eats, chats and has a good time
celebrating his release.  But a few
minutes after he went to bed, the
house was raided by the
Indian police who arrested Vinder.  Just
4 days later, the police conducted
another search at a new
house in Halldwine where Banmit had
settled after the first search.
There, the authorities discovered a device
containing more than 268 Bitcoins, which they
immediately linked to
badminton activities under the pseudonym Liston.
This of course led to
Badmith's arrest, who once again finds himself
in prison.  The only difference
is that this time, both brothers
are behind bars.  What is
particularly interesting is that
the press release from the
Department of Justice states
that the investigation was opened at the request
of the United States.  This could
suggest that the United States did
not intend to let Sin recover
the other half of his bitcoins and that he
indirectly wanted to arrest his
brother Parvinder as well.  Other
rumors even go so far as to suggest that
the Bitcoins were placed there by
Indian authorities because the
United States simply wanted to see
Parinder in prison.  In any case,
the trial concerning this matter is
still ongoing.  And even though Banmth
has already served time in
English and American prisons, he and his
brother could be sentenced to a
new term in India.  Of course, the
Indian authorities want to
confiscate the remaining 3600 bitcoins, which are
now worth nearly 230
million euros.  The
question is therefore whether they
will ever manage to recover these
bitcoins and even if Banmit and Parinder
actually possess them.
Thank you for watching this video and
thank you to Nord VPN for supporting my
projects.  Don't forget, you get 4 months
free on 2-year subscriptions.
Everything is in the description.  If you
want to discover another
equally crazy story, I recommend this
video in which, in 2010, a student
published a series of videos on YouTube.
At the time, it went almost unnoticed.
However, they attract the attention of
her university and then the police.
A few months later, in 23 seconds,
this student would change the course of an entire
country.