Did you know that your 10th message to
Claude cost 11 times more than your
first? Not because Anthropic is charging
you more, it's because Claude re-reads
your entire chat history before replying
to the message that you just sent. I
used to hit Claude's usage limits every
single day. However, after implementing
a few practical rules for how I use
Claude, I haven't hit my limits in over
a week. So, without further ado, here
are the 11 things I changed that stopped
me from hitting Claude's usage limits.
Oh, and if we haven't met yet, I'm Duby.
I build apps every day using Claude and
I've generated 47 thousand dollars in
less than 50 days using these AI tools.
So, first thing I need you to do in
order to save your precious Claude usage
is you need to stop looking at it as how
many messages you sent and instead look
at how many tokens you use. Because
Claude doesn't count messages, it counts
tokens. A token is roughly 3/4 of a
word, so a 100-word message is about 130
tokens. Every time you send a message,
Claude re-reads the entire conversation
from the top.
So, your first message costs maybe 500
tokens, your second message costs 1,000,
your 10th message costs 5,000, and your
30th? That's 232,000 tokens for one
message. A developer named Aniket
Parihar actually tracked this. 98.5% of
his tokens went to re-reading old
conversation history, only 1.5% went to
generating the actual response. That
means for every 100 tokens you're
burning, only one and a half are doing
useful work. That's not Claude being
stingy, that's you feeding it a novel
every time you ask a question. Once you
understand this, everything will change
because every single rule I'm about to
give you comes back to this one idea:
use fewer tokens per interaction. And
just like the tokens you put in count
against you, the inverse is also true.
Every word Claude sends back counts as
well. So, check out this repo called
Caveman. It makes Claude drop the fluff
and talk, well, like a caveman. People
have reported token reductions of up to
65% from using this alone. I'll leave a
link in the description. Rule one, don't
follow up. This is the one that saved me
the most tokens immediately. When Claude
gets something wrong, your instinct is
to send a correction. No, I meant this.
Uh, that's not what I wanted. Try this
instead. Don't do that. Every subsequent
message gets added to the conversation
history and remember, Claude re-reads
all of it every single turn. So, you're
burning tokens on context that didn't
even help. At five messages deep, you're
already at 7,500 tokens. So, instead of
correcting Claude with a follow-up,
click edit on your original message, fix
the wording, hit regenerate, the old
exchange gets replaced instead of
multiplied. Exact same result, but for a
fraction of the cost. Rule number two, a
fresh chat every 15 to 20 messages.
Imagine a chat with 100-plus messages.
That's over 2.5 million tokens burned.
Most of it just re-reading old history.
So, ideally, start a new chat every 15
to 20 messages. When a conversation gets
long, ask Claude to summarize
everything. Copy that summary, start a
new chat, and paste it as your first
message. You keep the context, you ditch
the bloat. I started doing this and my
limit warnings basically disappeared
overnight. Rule number three, batch your
questions into one message. Many people
believe that splitting questions into
separate messages leads to a better
result. Almost always, the opposite is
true. Three separate prompts equals
three context loads. One prompt with
three tasks equals one context load. You
save tokens twice. Fewer context reloads
and you stay further from hitting your
limit. Instead of summarize this
article, now list the main point, now
suggest a headline sent separately,
instead just write summarize this
article, list the main points, and
suggest a headline. And guess what? The
answers often turn out better because
Claude immediately sees the full
picture. Three questions, one prompt,
always. Four, track your token usage.
[music]
Claude doesn't show you how many tokens
you're actually using. Just a progress
bar that says 63% used. That's it. So, a
developer called Paweł Huryn built a
local dashboard that reads files Claude
Code already writes to your machine.
Turns out, every session, every turn,
every single token is logged to your
machine in JSONL files. Input tokens,
output tokens, cache reads, cache
creation, model names, timestamps, it's
all there. You just can't see it. The
dashboard scans those local files,
builds a database, and serves charts on
localhost. You can filter by model,
filter by time range, cost estimates
based on current API pricing, works
retroactively on your entire Claude Code
history. It's free, open source, zero
dependencies, you just need Python. You
can't fix what you can't measure.
Install it, look at your actual numbers,
and I guarantee you'll be shocked at
where your tokens are actually going.
Rule number five, upload recurring files
to projects. If you upload the same PDF
to multiple chats, Claude re-tokenizes
that document every single time. Use the
projects feature instead. Upload your
file once, it gets cached. Every new
conversation inside that project
references without burning tokens again.
Cached project content doesn't eat into
your usage when you access it
repeatedly. If you work with contracts,
briefs, style guides, or any long
documents, this alone could cut your
token spend dramatically. Rule number
six, set up memory and user preferences.
Every new chat without saved context
wastes three to five messages on setup.
I'm a marketer, I write in a casual
style. I prefer short paragraphs. You've
probably seen people start every prompt
with act as a professional whatever.
That's token burned on repeat. Claude
can actually remember this permanently.
Go to settings, then memory and user
settings, save your role, communication
style, and settings once. Claude will
automatically apply them to every new
chat. Rule number seven, turn off
features you're not actually using.
Things like web search, connectors, and
explore mode, all of these add tokens to
every response, even if you don't use
them. For example, if you're writing
your own content, turn off the search
and tools feature. The advanced thinking
feature also consumes tokens. Keep it
turned off by default. Only turn it on
if your first attempt was
unsatisfactory. The rule of thumb is if
you didn't turn this feature on
intentionally, just turn it off. Eight,
use Haiku for simple tasks. Grammar
checking, brainstorming, formatting,
quick translations, short answers, Haiku
handles all of this at a much lower cost
than Sonnet or Opus. Choosing the right
model is the most important decision you
make every single day. Haiku for drafts
and simple tasks frees up 50 to 70% of
your budget for tasks that truly require
powerful models. The way that I look at
it is Haiku is for quick tasks, it's low
cost. Sonnet is for real work, medium
cost. Opus is for deep thinking and high
cost. You don't need powerful models for
simple tasks. Rule nine, and this one
might sound obvious, but spread your
work across the day. The Claude system
uses a rolling 5-hour window. It does
not reset at midnight. Your limit
gradually decreases. Messages sent at
9:00 a.m. will no longer count by 2:00
p.m. If you use up your entire limit
during a single morning session, most of
your daily limit will remain unused.
Divide your day into two to three
sessions, morning, afternoon, and
evening. By the time you return, your
previous usage is no longer counted and
you have a new limit. Quick cheat code,
set a cron job to literally just ping
Claude with one tiny message at 6:00
a.m. while you're still in bed. Your
5-hour window starts then, not when you
sit down to work. So, if you hit your
limit at 10:00 a.m., your reset lands at
11:00. 10, work during off-peak hours.
Starting March 26, 2026, Anthropic will
now use up your 5-hour session limit
more quickly during peak hours. 5:00
a.m. to 11:00 a.m. Pacific time, 8:00
a.m. to 2:00 p.m. Eastern time on
weekdays. Same query, same chat, but
during peak hours, it impacts your limit
more. Your weekly limit remains the
same, but how it's distributed has
changed. Running resource-intensive
tasks in the evening or on weekends will
significantly stretch your plan. If
you're outside the US and Europe, Latin
America, or Asia, peak hours may
actually fall during your afternoon, so
check the calculation based on time
zones. If you're like me and you live in
Australia, your off-peak hours are
actually in the morning and in the
midday. That is usually when you can use
Claude without any worries. Rule 11,
enable extra usage as a safety net.
Subscribers to the Pro or Max plan can
enable the overage feature in the
settings usage section. When your
session limit is reached, Claude won't
block your access. It will switch to
pay-as-you-go billing at API rates. You
set a monthly spending limit to avoid
unexpected bills. This isn't about
saving tokens, it's about not losing
your work at the worst possible moment.
At first, it will be very difficult to
follow all the rules, but once you can
apply them automatically, you'll almost
never hit your limits. You might even
switch from the Max plan to a regular
one. You'll have plenty of tokens to
use. Now, whenever you see your usage
limits go up, just remember, Claude
doesn't count your messages, it counts
your tokens.