[music]
for gagner big géant de la tech
transaction milliard titan de la fin un
terrain de jeu la bourse une monnaie
d'échange l'information there are big houses, giant analyst teams, giant profit teams behind them, competing with them is
very difficult,
les petits investisseurs peuventils
suivre le rythme comment s'informer les
réseaux sociaux sont  Actuellement
dominés par les sujets
But that is often exactly what subsequently
performs poorly.
Comment les investisseurs privés obtienn
les informations dont ils ont besoin?
Comment survival in a combat souvent
inégal?
[music]
My name is Matthias Schmidt.  I am
49 years old and a private investor.
Mathias is a small
porter, a participatory investor who
invests in argent, without being
consequential, principally in the
actions in the bourse.
Il a commencé très jeune.  It's now
a long day on the long course.
The first time I became interested in stocks
was in 1987 after the
stock market crash.  That's when my father
bought his first shares in Anand from the bank advisor.  I was 11 years old at the time.  I
then started reading everything in
the city library about the stock market
and economics.  Uh, I
participated in stock market games,
read magazines, and gradually
worked my way into it.  On
paper, everything worked out quite well.
Mathias is lanced along the way of the
boursiers
and the apprendation of the debut of
his investment is not as simple as it is
always with success.
The day after my 18th birthday,
I placed my first order, which
was for an option certificate. That
option certificate was a
total loss,
and then a few months later I bought a second
certificate with higher leverage and a
shorter term, and that one also went bust. After that,
I was pretty much done with it, and
that paid off.  That was, um, a pretty
good start, actually.  Mathias a tire
of the leçons de ses échecs.
Aujourd'hui, il is rend à une réunion
d'actionnaire.  It arrives in the life of the
investor after a long period of time
and in the department, the tire and the savoir of the
books.
That's when I bought my first good stocks
: Microsoft, Intel, Oracle,
McDonald's.  Those were the
values ​​at the time when
I really
started to get serious.  Dansercheitinvestiss
porteur fait à a gigantesque industrial financière.
Les companies like Black Rock or les
grandes banks employ an armée
d'analystes qui surveill en permanence
les marchés financiers.
Selon Lafama, the European Association
of Gestionnaires de Funds and Actors,
environs 130,000 employees and 4,600
companies working directly in
the domain of investment
across Europe.  Elles y gèrent plus de
23000 billions d'euros.
Les chiffres sont encore plus
impressionnants si on regarde du côté
des États-Unis ou de l'Asie.
Mathias lui fait cavalier seul.  The
souhaite investir son argent de manière
indépendante et se renseigne en
permanence sur ses investments.
Aujour'hui, it returns to a
company that doesn't take action.
Ce ne sont pas les particuliers mais les
grands actors qui dominant les grandes
places boursières du monde.  [snort]
Les investisseurs institutionalnel comme
les fonds d'investissement, les caisses
de retraite, les banques ou compagnies
d'assurance gèrent des milliards qu'il
placent en grande partie en bourse.
Leurs decisions peuvent fortement
influencer les cours parce qu'ils
disposent souvent d'un access privilégié
aux entreprises et aux responsables
politiques.
Les particuliers qui investissent
directement des summers plus modestes n'ont
en revanche qu'un poids limité sur
les cours des petites entreprises.
Karol Brodziński, 34 years old, analityk
akcji zajmujący się sectorem bankowym.
Carol Broginski works in the
current finance sector in Switzerland and is now
renting in the country with the same origins as
possible
[music].  You
can also get to the bottom of the
pieniędzy, które w wieku 16 lat po raz
pierwszy
zainwestowałem w akcje polskich spółek.
Większość akcji, większość spółek, które
kupiłem potem w 2007 i w 2008
straciło na wartości.
Więc to była pierwsza lekcja
na temat tego,
że rynek potraffi być trudny i że potraffi
zaskakiwać w szczególności osoby
niedoświadczone.
Les analystes comme Carole évaluent les
companies.  Ils read leurs bilan, se rendent
dans leurs locaux et suivent les
évolutions du marché dans leur secteur
respectif.  Les gestionnaires de fonds
constituent ensuite of the portfolios en
fonction de leur recommendation.
The investors can take part and
acquire a part.  Les conseillers
bancaires leur recommend ensuite les
produits financiers les mieux adaptés à
leurs besoins, c'est-à-dire des parts de
fonds, des actions ou des obligation
individually
Carole is a professionnel and a donc
accès aux companies.  If you are an
analyst, you are in contact with a
company that recommends you to large
investors.
Quand ces derniers achètent beaucoup
d'actions, ils font monter le cours.  The
CD Project company is a producer of
video games connected to the world.
The value in the bourse is valued at 7
billions of American dollars.
The series of video games The Witcher has a
large contribution to this success, and is
part of the 3rd opus.
In this era, Carol analyzed the
companies in the technology and
video games sector in Polon.
Bzo dobo
mocne zainteresowanie strony inwestorów
zagranicznych,
dużych zagranicznych funduszy w
oczekiwaniu na kolejną grę.  [music]
Les attentes desamers visavis duer
produit déterminent le succès de l'
entreprise et donc aussi celui de l'
action.
The premiere version of The Witcher
was released in 2007, CD Project was
not available on the market.  The success in this
modéré à cela is based on the
global financial crisis.
PD Michel Nowakowski has to go through the process of writing in
the language, so that it can be used in a short time, but it is also
possible to use the financial resources and the
financial resources  projektów, która była dla
nas kluczowa dla
facto tak bezdy.
Never byłoby nas tu, gdzie jesteśmy w tej
chwili, ponieważ nie mieliśmy po prostu
finansowania.  Głda pomogła nam pozyskać
finansowanie na na dokończenie projektu.
To był Wilbin 2 w tamtym czasie, co było
kluczowe dla dla przetrwania i dalszego
rozwoju
spóki.  [music]
Depuis, tout va bien pour CD Project
malgré les fluctuations ponctuelles du
cours de l'action quand des problems
surviennent au lancement d'un new
jeu vidéo.
The names of the factors are determined
in the analysis of Carole.
wycenie
tych firm jest ich zdolność do
generowania
gotówki, do gerowania przepływów
pieniężnych
i ta zdolność,
ta analiza odnosi się do przyszłości, do do
przyszłych przepływów pieniężnych.
Więc kluczowym elementem jest spojrzenie
na strategi
Mathias Schmid l'investisse particulier
se lui aussi dans les entreprises
comme il vit de ses investissements il
suit [music] de près chacun d'entre eux
il mise sur des actions With large ones,
Amazon, [music] an
Apple Nvidia
to achieve an advantage there with your own research is extremely
difficult.
Depuis des années, il participe aux
assemblées générales des petites
entreprises comme aujourd'hui à cell de
DFAM.
This société achète des biens
commercial real estate, les r et les
lois des enseignes et des supermarchés.
I hereby cheerfully open
the regular main supply of the
Pharma Deutsche Fachmarktang at 11 a.m.  Le risque?
On specule souvent sur ce type de
petites entreprises car il faut
relativement peu d'argent et d'
investisseurs pour faire bouger les
cours.  Mathias Schmidth does not have
information on the internet, in the
special media on the commerce register and
on the action of
the general assembly.  I noticed in the
annual report that
some properties are in the GmbH, very
few, and the others are in the GmbH and
Kokag.  I'd be interested to know the reason behind that
.
Mathiasrada is the fondateur and
president of DFAMA.  Schmidt has a
habitué des lieux, he connaît depuis
des années.  En tant qu'actionnaire
principal, Schrade détient la majorityité
des parts de l'entreprise.
His primary interest lies in
his 26% stake in the company.
This is in line with what we
have as other shareholders, and
I consider that to be very, very important.
assister à l'assemblée generale il faut
une action
marie j'ai 30 ans et je suis analyse
[music]
chercheur
marie s'intéresse elle aussi entreprises
non pas pour son propre compte mais en
tant qu'analyste indépendante mandaté.
This sont souvent des investisseurs
professionnels, donc fond
d'investissement Family Office,
Advisers et puis il y a aussi des gens
qui sont fortunes [snort] qui
ensuite veulent investir à leur tour
dans des entreprises, dans des startups.
The French young man has a fair
place in the finance industry margin
.
Grâce à son analysis personalized
d'entreprise soigneusement sélectionnée,
elle accompagne ses clients dans leur
décision d'investissement.
Elle peut compter pour cela sur un
talent particulier qu'elle cultive
depuis l'enfance.
J'ai passé beaucoup de temps avec les
adultes part que j'étais la petite
dernière d'une grande famille et donc je
parlais pas beaucoup mais j'observais
énormément et
donc j'ai pu apprendre à analyzer des
situations
et ça m'aide beaucoup aujourd'hui dans
mon  travail.
Pour Marie, the analysis is not limited to the
codes and visits to the
company.
This method also includes observation of the
terrain.  Elle scrute le comportement des
clients, les flux de marchandises et les
stratégies de vente directement dans la
rue.
This is an idea for the trends in
consumption not only at the level of
agate de luxe.  The line of attention, the
file of attention for Louis Viton, is
also an indication.  Est-ce que les gens viennent
faire des dépenses
discrétionnaires ou pas sur du luxe ou
pas?  Le côté Zara, this is plutôt de la
fashion.  Don't forget to
see the name of the bag and have a
comment on the consumption of other goods
.  Les professionnels comme
Marie qui étudi régulièrement ses
données dans les régions du monde
peuvent ainsi identifier [music] les
tendances.
The rémunération de ces analyzes varied
considerablement en fonction de la
charge de travail et de l'ampleur de l'
investissement.
It all costs €500 for a premier budget of
€20,000 for an
analysis approach, including [music] and
a study of the terrain for the account of
its clients.
Et à ce momentl [music] also, je les
aide à comprendre a petit peu quels
sont les enjeux de l'entreprise dans
laquelle ils veulent investir.
Ce travail ne rapporte pas à Marie des
Revenus coloss mais elle est moins
dépendante des gros actors du secteur
financier.
Passionné for l'investissement privé,
Carol is naturally oriented towards
a career in finance.  Très
ambitious, il a étudié à Varsovie,
Francfort et Saal [music] avant de
travailler pour plusieurs institutions
financières de premier plan.
Son experience d'analyste lui a permis
de se créer un réseau quii ouvre
désormais les portes du center
névralgique de la finance polonaise.  The
bourse de Varsovie
polski rynek jest nadal relatyw [music]
małym rynkiem.  Jeśli chodzi o
uczestników rynku, to jest to [musik]
dość mała grupa ludzi i w momencie kiedy
ktoś
wchodzi do tej branzo szybko ma
możliwość poznać w zasadzie wszystkich.
The Varsovie bourse is one of the
places in the world that connects the
croissance with rapid activity.
[music]
Sous le régime communiste, il n'y avait
pas de bourse en Pologne.  Elle n'a
rouvert qu'en 1991 [music]
après le changement de système.
In the hall, Carol Croise Valdemar
Markevic, president of the association
of courtiers, is also a member of the
conseil d'administration de la plus
grande banque polonaise.
Il les a rencontré tous les deux
lorsqu'il était analy en Polonie.
jest dynamiczne, bo banki finansują
tradycyjne przedsiębiorstwa, but never
dostarczają capital wyższego ryzyka,
które są kluczowe dla innowacyjnych,
najbardziej dynamicznych
firm.  This is the typical European
currency.  What is the cost
of the bank, and what about
Niemiec, Prawda?  Bo Niemcy,
jak już się do czegoś przyzwyczają, to
tak zostaje, nie?  How dominacja kredytu
bankowego jest głównym problemsem.
zwiększeniu innowacyjności generalnie
europejskiej gospodarki.  Jeszcze ciekawą
statystykę czytałem i to jest tak
production gap powiększający się między gospodarką europejską na
korzyść amerykańskiej
l'économie polonaise estune des flores d'Europe de
plus en plus d'investisseurs se
tournent vers le marché local [music]
the majority of the capitaux proviennent de l'
étranger
en 2025 l'indice boursier a augmenté de
plus de 40%
Barilovski director de la bourse très
confiant
carolet dans son bureau qui donne sur le
paradny
ziok
zielony kolor jest ważny na giełdzie bo
oznacza wzrosty  więc miło z nim prbywać
jest na co dzień
Polonie les
jeunes
[music]
zrobiliśmy badanie ankiety wśród wśród
młodych ludzi i okazuje się że ich
cele czy myślenie o inwestowaniu jest
bardzo dojrzałe przebija  się does
inwestowanie na emeryturę już w takim
młodym wieku inwestowanie na potrzeby
życiowe, a w mniejszym stopniu no taka chęć
szybko
Aujour'h les néoclications
permettent d'acheter des actions sans
passer par les banques traditionallynell ce qui
incite  davantage de particuliers  à
investir par eux une tendance renforcée
par les crypton naturalnie bitcoinorzy
wyobraenia tak rozbudza wyobraźnię i
przez to jest atrakcyjny dla wielu
młodych ludzi jeżeli by to dobrze
wykorzystać żeby
promować edukację wśród  młodych ludzi
jak chodzi o inwestycje kapitałowe.
Znaczy wydaje mi się, że to może pomagać
rynkowi kapitałowit
danset univers de la finance eter à
influencer le marché en représentant des
grands actors
return dans le monde plus modeste des [
musik] petits investisseurs au siège
defama caché dans un quartier
résidentiel de  Berlin.
Mathias Schmidrouve Mathias Schrade, the
general manager of the company in
the sous-sol of this maison.
The atmosphere is très détendue.  Pourquoi
le PDG-il the company depuis endroit?
Well, as a Swabian, it's already
clear that one tends to look more closely at costs
.
But it also simply has to do with
quality of life.  When I finish
work, I just have to
walk around the house once and I'm already home.
Schmid
has the discipline to see it through.
Person l'entreprise compte que 50
employés.  [music] Elle possède plus de
90 d'une valeur totale de plus de 340
million d'euros.  Lower limit.  Our
largest location is actually, um,
time.  Time is, um, a Kaufland.  If
you zoom in a little, you can
see it even better, and the property
has an annual rent of around one and a half
million.  Change may also be an
entrepreneur who Schrade is also an
influencer who appeals to the people in the
makroom.  [music]
works in such a way that
if I drive past the gas station this morning
and decide whether to buy
thanks today or
leave the tank empty for three weeks, I
ultimately influence inflation, the
demand for oil.  Um, that means every
single decision made by 8 billion
people in the world has a
different impact on this
macro data.  Ultimately, it's
madness to try and make a
reasonable prediction about such a huge aggregated number.
Inflation, Croissance or geopolitics.
All these elements are part of the
macroeconomic data that influences
the course of action.
L'ambiance sur les marchés boursiers est
souvent influence par la politique.  In
April 2025, the announcement of the new
measures of the
American President Donald Trump [music]
a fait chuter les cours dans le monde
entier.  Les droits de douanes perturbent
les échanges et réduisent les profits
des entreprises.
Quelques semaines plus [ __ ], the advertisement
of leur gel a product l'effet inverse.
Les investisseurs privés sont
généralement trop lents pour en profiter
car les géants réagissent beaucoup plus
rapidement que
les investisseurs privés peuvent
également s'adresser à des
professionnels.  For example, as a
conseiller bancaire, my customer
is a seller.  [music] En effet,
les sociétés de fonds versent des
commissions aux banques quand celles-ci
vendent leurs products, qu'il conviennent
ou non à l'investisseur.
Au Pays-Bas et au Royaume-Uni, this
practice is interdite.
An initiative aimed at interfacing with
Europe is also an option.  The lobby
bancaire qui perçoit des commissions
estant trop puissant dans des pays comme
l'Allemagne ou la France.
Matthus Schmidtus
Schmid chairman of the board of the Quirin
Private [music]
in Allemagne qui ves clients de products
financiers pour lesquels elle perçoit
des commissions.  Ici tout repose sur la
quality [music] du conseil.
It's no use if the
financial industry gives bad advice
, because in the end it leads to so much
disappointment and people either turn away
completely or do everything
themselves.  And we saw that in England
.  There, the industry itself
said, let's
abolish commissions.
Porteurs with a modest patrimoine not
benéficient plus d'aucun de ces
conseils.
The commissions tell us that they are
pratiquées by banks in English and
French and are not
obligatory.
Ici les investisseurs pai pour le
conseil.  That makes a net worth of
€200,000.  And these are precisely the people
who say, I need another
person to guide me through this
jungle of capital markets.  Lain
Bank recommends the panion and the ETF and
not the individual values.
Pour les investisseurs privés, il est
difficile de s'y retrouver dans la
jungle des offres et des prestataires.
Mathias Schmid comes
to Stuttgart curieux and is very vigilant in the
course of the stands.
Before letting yourself be persuaded or doing anything at such a trade fair,
it is
important to always ask yourself: Do
I understand the product and how does
this supplier make their money?  What is his
interest in selling me
this particular product or strategy
?  D'autant plus qu'on y
trouve de all des matières premières
alors en passant par les pierres
précieuses.  We are now talking about
diamonds, which are often sold as an investment
, but clearly diamonds are
not an investment and belong on the hand
of a beautiful woman, but not in an
investment portfolio.
Nothing is lost because expertise
is needed, because so much
depends on the cut and purity, and
we as private investors
cannot judge that at all.   The
coalition agreement
contains clauses that don't
say anything.  The price and the amount of gain are
exploited by the commercial fins.
The systems of trading and
financial products that allow the realization
of normal profits are
proposed.
The term "financial pornography" exists for a
reason.  There are so many
different players in this market,
and much of it is pure
entertainment, and you really have to
see it that way.  The situation is
particulièrement critique sur internet.
La plupart des young investisseurs
cherchent des opportunités d'achat d'
action.  In court, the
risk of making a decision quickly arises.
Social media works best when I
discuss values ​​and topics that are currently on
everyone's lips.  But that's
often exactly what results in poor
performance later on.  I actually need to
act when nobody is
interested, when I have peace and quiet
to look at the value, when I can trade
without having to chase after the price
.  [music] De plus, des prestataires
peu sérieux et des criminals y pululent,
profitant de l'opacité du réseau pour
commettre fraude et escroquerie.
Gagner beaucoup d'argent without effort.
C'est avec this promise that certain
financers, des influenceurs financiers
attirent les utilisateur sur leur site
car chaque clic compte.  The benéficie
d'un public nombreux and de revenus
publicitaires élevés.   D'
autres proposent des séminaires hors
de prix ou des tools peu efficaces pour
analyser les actions ou faire du
trading.  Ou alors, ils attirent leur
lecteur vers d'autres sites proposant
des offres similaires et perçoivent des
commissions grâce au lien d'affiliation.
Cela devient criminal lorsque de fausses
informations sont diffusées pour
influencer les cours, notamment via de
faux comptes qui usurpent l'identité de
finenceur sérieux ou avec de fausses
vidéos généré par I.
Fake accounts are a huge problem in
social media because it is very easy
to copy the content.  But
basically, anyone who travels with a watchful eye will
recognize some
warning signs.  And the first thing is that
a reputable finfluencer will never
contact followers and
directly offer them any investment opportunities.
Smith is a lui-même blogueur amateur sur
internet and possède son propre groupe
Facebook.   There is something to be said for the greatness of
this activity.  The aim is simple, part of
its connaissances and souhaite
avant tout apprendre des other things.  For
example, Jonathan Neuchler, a
professional influencer and
déjà emcee, is very connected and has a great deal of grace
.  With me, there are
no red flashing lights
or dubious promises.
Furthermore, I don't see myself as a recommendation
service, but as a
financial education platform, a
community where people
can exchange ideas.
The community is a swarm where
everyone benefits from being
part of it.  Yes,
many of the stocks we've featured originated from within
the community
.  I initiate this with a
post where I share my research,
and then
experienced investors, both positive and negative, or
even young investors who understand new trends, come forward from the left and right,
and then I am
much wiser than before.
Les échanges directs avec d'autres
investisseurs privés sont plus
enrichissants car plus fiables.  Mathias
Schmid organizes the régulièrement of the
round tables.  Il invite également des
entrepreneurs comme le director de
Mathias
comme beaucoup d'autres il connais
longtemps.   It
starts with me having a friend from my
town who lived at 200, with whom I
played in the sandbox, because we are only
half a year apart.  He ended up
joining the group by chance, including people
I know from my studies.  There's one of them who
's now a pension fanatic.
Même Carl Mathus Schmid, leur de BE
la consacrée au chiffres, au tendan au
rapport annuel.  The object is improved
without being invested.  Pour
Mathias, il s'agit de la clé de l'
indépendance financière.
the up.
I have been dealing with
the topic of finance for almost 37 or 38 years now.
Freedom is really the key point.
It's simply the freedom to do what you want to do
, what you enjoy.
I have the advantage that I've
never really had to work in my life
because I've always done what
I enjoy.  [music]
Mais tout le monde n'aime pas éplucher
les rapports annuels autant que Mathias.
Face à la puissance et aux énormes
moyens de this industrie, les petits
porteurs ne peuvent pas rivaliser.
En revanche, ils sont bien plus libre
dans leur manière d'investir.  Certainly
acquire [music] because of its expertise
and its créent leur propre créneau.
The réseau and l'échange sont essential
car l'information reste pour eux also
the secret of success.
Black color.
[music]