For the past two years, something strange has been
happening.  Anyone can write an
argumentative text, produce
functional code, write a
structured analysis.
Visible skill has become
accessible, and yet a large part
of these productions serve no purpose.
They are correct, they are
fluid, they seem professional,
and they miss their target.  Something is
missing.  Something that is not
found in the tool or in the
prompt.  Something we could
n't get while we thought we were paying for something else
.  But what
exactly are we paying for?  Let's take a simple scene.
Two people use exactly the
same AI model on the same day for the
same task.  The first option yields a
useful, precise,
context-appropriate and relevant document.  The second one
obtains a document that appears to be correct
.
But unusable, too generic, off-
topic or just wrong, under a layer of
confidence.
How can such a difference be explained?
Not in the tool, it is identical, not
in the prompt, even if we like to
think so.  So, where exactly?  before the
request in the way of framing the
problem and after the response in the
ability to recognize if it is
good.
The first person knows what they are
looking for and they know what they are looking at.
The second one knows neither one nor the other.
This is where something
important is at stake.  We are confusing two
operations that we have hitherto treated
as one: producing and judging.
For a very long time, the two went
together.  To produce something
good, one needed judgment capable of
guiding the production.  To judge, one
had to have produced something.  The two were
welded together.  Lia comes to separate them.  She
takes the visible half, the production,
and leaves the other half exposed.
This other half is called
discernment.  Ultimately, it is she who decides
whether the work has value or not.
And it is she who makes the
difference between the two people on
our scene today.  We often hear the
phrase "LIA replaces the expert".  This
statement is partly true and partly
misleading.  Misleading because it
assumes something that has never
really been verified, that we knew what
an expert was.  But did we
really know that?  Over decades,
expertise was presented as a
two-tiered package.  On the first floor,
the ability to produce, write a
report, write code, design a
plan, build an analysis.  On the
second floor, a less
visible ability: knowing what to produce, knowing how to
recognize when it's good.  Knowing when
to stop, adjust, and start again.
This second floor was
rarely seen.  He was hidden behind the
first one and since we couldn't see him, we
ended up believing that the expert's value
lay entirely in his
output.
We paid for the deliverable, we paid for the
hours, we paid for the page, the code, the
report.  In reality, we were paying for something else
.  We were paying for the judgment that held it all
together.  But this judgment
remained invisible, integrated, blended into
the work.  And then Lia arrived,
she does one very specific thing.  It
causes the price of the first
floor to plummet.
Producing a well-reasoned text costs
almost nothing anymore.  Producing
functional code is no longer possible.  Producing a
structured analysis is no longer possible.  The first
floor becomes accessible to everyone and the
second floor suddenly appears.  Its
nature hasn't changed, its
price hasn't changed, it has simply become
visible.  What looks like a
replacement is actually a
revelation.
The expert is not replaced, he is
unmasked.  And what we discover is that
the value we had
always placed on it was not what we thought it was
.  We are seeing several of these kinds of revelations right now
.  Things we thought were
stable are shifting,
jobs we thought were solid are being
restructured, and things we no longer
questioned need to be re-
examined.  This channel exists for that purpose, not
to react to current events, not to
comment on the tools of the month, just to
take the time to clarify one
confusion at a time.  If this way of
looking at things resonates with you, you're in the right
place for what follows.  Let's get back to our
topic.  If we accept this revelation, we
can reconstruct a simple interpretation.
All intellectual work follows three
stages.  Framing, production,
validation, framing, it's about deciding what to
produce.  Asking the right
question: Identifying what matters and
what doesn't.  Knowing where you're going
before you leave.  The production was
carried out, transforming the intention into an
object.  Write, code, draw,
calculate.  Validation is about judging the
result.  Is that correct?
Is this relevant?  Does this
answer what we were
really looking for?  Lia occupies a massive position in the
middle, in production.  But when it comes to framing the problem,
she doesn't know how to formulate it correctly on her own
.  And for validation, she cannot
recognize on her own if her own
answer is correct.  These two extremes
remain human and they
now bear the full weight of value.
That's what we can call
discernment.
Discernment is not a
new skill, it is the old capacity of
the expert, the one that was never named
because it was submerged in
production.
Today, this capacity is becoming
legible.  It can be named, it
can be cultivated, it can be
priced for what it is.  To
show it, you have to make a small
move.  Stop selling
deliverables.
Start selling judgment applied
to a deliverable.  Stop saying "I
produced this".  Start saying in words, "I
decided this needed to be produced and
I recognized why the final version
was the right one. This shift is
small."  He is immense
in his posture.  He gives back to humans
what they had always done without ever
saying so.  One question remains.  A
question that will not be resolved.
Tonight, where does discernment come from?  It
historically comes from production.
We learn to judge because we have
produced.  Good work is recognized
because it involves having done bad work, then good work, and finally, just work
.  Production
was the silent school of judgment.
But Silia takes charge of production
from the apprenticeship, from the first
years of the profession, what happens?  We
may be creating a generation that
will judge without ever having produced anything.
People who are expected to evaluate without having done the work themselves.
Is this sustainable?  The question remains
open.  It deserves to be revisited.
Tell me what you think in the
comments.  I read and respond to all
your comments without exception.